<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hamhanded.ly</title>
    <description>Hi, I’m Patrick and mostly I make maps. I like working on projects where I can tell stories with data and teach others how to do the same.
</description>
    <link>http://hamhands.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://hamhands.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2015 11:01:12 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2015 11:01:12 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.5.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Making Tough Project Decisions in Pittsburgh</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/ben_fire.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ben hears from a Fire purchaser&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;My teammate Ben hears from a purchaser in the Pittsburgh Fire Bureau.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a month of building prototypes and soliciting feedback from our city partners in Pittsburgh, we’ve started to narrow the scope of what we want to build to help change the outdated ways the city buys everything from software to paperclips. Explicitly choosing not just what to work on, but what to stop actively developing is a difficult part of the user-centered design process. It’s also one of the reasons Code for America encourages fellowship teams to start building early, to get testable prototypes in front of users as soon as possible so that the hard work of scoping can happen sooner rather than later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the end of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codeforamerica.org/blog/2015/04/09/3-development-tips-from-team-pittsburgh-2/&quot;&gt;Ben’s post&lt;/a&gt; outlining the principles behind how we build, he listed five things we’ve built since arriving in January. Since that post was written, we went back to Pittsburgh and put some of those wireframes and early-stage applications in front of city staff, and the feedback was overwhelmingly positive. While this is great news, it also means we had to come up with another filter to help us make some tough decisions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;breadth-depth--lift&quot;&gt;Breadth, Depth, &amp;amp; Lift&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To guide our thinking, we adapted a set of metrics we learned from the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.codeforamerica.org/our-work/focus-areas/health/&quot;&gt;Code for America health team&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Breadth&lt;/em&gt;: how many people are impacted by a given problem?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Depth&lt;/em&gt;: how deeply is the problem is felt?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lift&lt;/em&gt;: how technically or politically difficult is the fix?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thinking in these terms helps us prioritize, particularly given the relatively narrow window we have in a fellowship year. Inverting &lt;em&gt;lift&lt;/em&gt; into a positive metric, we were able to start thinking in terms of &lt;em&gt;feasibility&lt;/em&gt;, looking to the likelihood of a successful deployment given both the technical demands as well as the surrounding organizational context. We then took our four major projects (a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buildpgh.com/beacon&quot;&gt;marketing/outreach site&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buildpgh.com/scout&quot;&gt;Wexplorer&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/codeforamerica/template-maker&quot;&gt;Template Maker&lt;/a&gt;, and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buildpgh.com/sherpa&quot;&gt;Pittsburgh Procurement Explorer&lt;/a&gt;) and gave them a high, medium, or low value for each category:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/project_matrix.png&quot; alt=&quot;Project Matrix&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Our decision-making metrics and projects, in one chart.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this line of thinking, we opened up a conversation about Template Maker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;rethinking-our-focus-on-documents&quot;&gt;Rethinking Our Focus on Documents&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After our initial conversations in February, we saw a huge need for common “templating” for all kinds of procurement documents. So we built a prototype:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/template_maker.gif&quot; alt=&quot;Template Maker&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;The functionality of Template Maker in action.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Template Maker, our city partners in the legal department could create a central database of internal procurement documents, which had the potential to transform the entire process. Standardized document templates would become forms, which could remove a lot of the confusion departments face while drafting requests for proposals (RFP), resulting in better documents and less legal back and forth during the final contracting process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But after looking at our projects using our decision-making categories, &lt;strong&gt;we decided to stop actively developing Template Maker&lt;/strong&gt;. Here’s why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lift required to bring Template Maker across the finish line is such that we would have to dedicate a majority if not 100 percent of our team’s focus to this single product. Making a &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WYSIWYG&quot;&gt;WYSIWYG&lt;/a&gt; editor for procurement documents that doesn’t just work, but is also enjoyable to use is no small feat and ends up replicating much of the same features many of our users already have access to in Microsoft Word or Google Docs. Template Maker also only addresses documents, just one part of the extremely lengthy and involved procurement process. In short, Template Maker would be a large investment for a relatively narrow outcome. By moving our focus off of documents, we can focus on the entire process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;next-directions&quot;&gt;Next Directions&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We think we can have a larger impact for a lower lift by focusing more of our technical efforts in and around city purchasing. Here’s where we’re going:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Expand Wexplorer into a searchable, categorizable, and regularly updated library of current contracts that department purchasers can use as part of their daily workflow.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Build a &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.buildpgh.com/beacon&quot;&gt;central Office of Management &amp;amp; Budget (OMB) site&lt;/a&gt; for marketing upcoming contracting opportunities using a combination of data from Wexplorer as well as department-generated content. A &lt;a href=&quot;http://pittsburghpa.gov/omb/contract-bids&quot;&gt;current site for professional service opportunities exists&lt;/a&gt;, but we think having commodity opportunities more actively marketed would deliver value for city departments.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Implement a data update workflow that not only helps OMB with shepherding contracts through the extremely complex purchasing process, but also keeps city apps up to date.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Move away from document-based solutions and explore alternative ways to guide city departments through the process.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Work with the legal team to help craft templates in tools city departments are already using.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are really excited to see where this readjustment of focus takes us. Stay tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
        <link>http://hamhands.github.io/words/making-tough-project-decisions-in-pittsburgh</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hamhands.github.io/words/making-tough-project-decisions-in-pittsburgh</guid>
        
        <category>Pittsburgh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Observations From the First Month</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/pgh_city_hall.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Shelly and Henry in City Hall&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’re officially into the final week of our residency month in Pittsburgh! Over the past 3+ weeks we’ve had the pleasure of meeting a ton of people who deal with purchasing in city government, as well as members of the business community, and have learned a lot about what works well, as well as how the process could be improved. In these conversations, a few common themes have come up that we wanted to pass along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In no particular order, here are some of the main things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;it-is-difficult-for-city-purchasers-to-find-out-what-is-on-contract&quot;&gt;It is difficult for city purchasers to find out what is on contract.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve known since day 1 that this was an issue (we even built our first app to help address it), but we never fully grasped how the lack of a searchable list of current contracts can slow down everyday purchasing. When a purchaser for a given department wants to buy something on contract, they have to consult a spreadsheet of nearly 500 contracts, none of which are categorized or itemized. What this means in practice is that a lot of purchases go to companies that a purchase has experience working with rather than the one that offers the best price, service, quality, etc., etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps more noteworthy is how many purchasers go to Staples for their office supplies, mostly because they can search for items individually and are told immediately whether it’s on contract or not. They may be able to get a given item at a better price elsewhere, but the time they save by going to one vendor with a good inventory is worth it to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;new-contracts-take-a-long-time-to-process-and-often-attract-relatively-few-companies&quot;&gt;New contracts take a long time to process and often attract relatively few companies.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Putting a contract out to bid is a pain. Responding to a bid is a pain. We’ve heard voices on both sides of contracting that have said the entire process is extremely onerous, takes too long, and in the end doesn’t always yield the best results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One issue that stood out in many conversations is advertising. First, apart from the local newspaper, there doesn’t seem to be one central channel or mailing list for businesses to learn about new opportunities. There is a $49/year online subscription service, but not only do businesses have to pay for this information, but they also have to provide their tax identification number, social security number, and other personal information to sign up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lengthy internal process outlined above is often accompanied by a relatively compressed advertising period, sometimes as low as two weeks. The reason behind this is unclear, but it struck us as less than optimal. It’s possible that long internal wait times put pressure on departments to push the process along, directly chipping away at the window for businesses to learn about and respond to open bids. Whatever the reason, speeding up the internal workings while lengthening the external advertising period seems necessary. This, combined with better advertising channels would likely be a marked improvement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;buying-off-contract-happens--a-lot&quot;&gt;Buying off-contract happens – A lot!&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps unsurprisingly, rather than going through the process of establishing a new contract, departments use other channels to get what they need quickly, even for things they buy all the time. The explanatory purchasing process (i.e. petty cash) is one of these channels and it seems to be commonly used across the board to buy supplies needed to do business. Most of the people we’ve talked to aren’t happy with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one, the maximum for any explanatory purchase is capped at $2000. This would be fine if actually used in petty cash scenarios, but many departments are using explanatory purchases to cover essential supplies. The competitive bid threshold (i.e. when departments need to put a contract out to bid) is set at $30,000, but there isn’t a functional alternative for repeat purchases not already under contract. To avoid having to go through a complex and lengthy contracting process, purchasers choose the less immediately painful option.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A second pain point is the oversight that accompanies explanatory purchases. Since it was set up to cover petty cash situations, all explanatory purchases have to be signed off by the departmental director, then forwarded to the Office of Management &amp;amp; Budget, then to City Council who approve a long list of explanatory purchases on a weekly basis, all by interoffice mail. Not only is this a lot of work, but it’s also a lot of wait:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I’m waiting 2, 3 weeks on life-saving medical equipment every few weeks. My biggest aggravation is sending forms downtown for things that I’ve bought before, and will buy again and again.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As one of our interviewees notes above, the explanatory process is a big source of frustration. While it may not be as locally painful as putting a contract out to bid, the aggregate impact on the system is significant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/pgh_omb.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Ben meets with OMB&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;whats-next&quot;&gt;What’s next?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good question! Now that our “listening tour” is wrapping up, we’re looking forward to coming back with some concrete improvements to some of the problems outlined above. The Code for America fellowship is a unique opportunity to build solutions starting with user experience first, which requires us to some extent put aside our desire to always be building things. Over the coming months, we’ll be putting some of our ideas in front of both those within city government as well as business owners to test what we come up with. We’ve already had a ton of fruitful conversations with people who tend to not do much work together, so we can’t wait to see what happens when we can actually have them use what we build.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until then,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Patrick, Team PGH&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 23 Feb 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://hamhands.github.io/words/observations-from-the-first-month</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hamhands.github.io/words/observations-from-the-first-month</guid>
        
        <category>Pittsburgh</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Announcing New Spatial Web Services</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As has been noted &lt;a href=&quot;http://phillyinnovates.com/2013/08/20/empowering-civic-leaders-neighborhood-heroes/&quot;&gt;on this blog before&lt;/a&gt;, making data available in formats that are easily consumable is an important piece of the larger open data project. Serving up data that can be incorporated into projects quickly and easily not only helps citizenry better understand our world, but provides a connection to government at all levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But open data doesn’t end there. If we are to &lt;a href=&quot;http://phillyinnovates.com/2014/01/14/from-open-data-to-big-data/&quot;&gt;release with intent&lt;/a&gt;, we should consider the consumers of our data the way software developers consider their end-users. What will be done with the data once consumed? How will it be queried? How will it be organized? These questions guide our releases, but perhaps more importantly highlight the need for continual dialogue in providing data that better suits the consumer’s needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/parks_map.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Philly Parks Map&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Parks map with the newly available State Senate Districts.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In answering questions of organization, one of the most effective ways to group large datasets is by spatial boundary. While the lines by which we organize data spatially can often be somewhat subjective, from an administrative standpoint, boundaries have clear significance that can be felt. From collecting taxes, to assigning policing responsibilities, to funding schools, boundaries matter because we as a society say they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, we have a number of &lt;a href=&quot;http://gis.phila.gov/arcgis/rest/services/PhilaOIT-GIS_Boundaries/MapServer&quot;&gt;geographic boundaries&lt;/a&gt; available for public use, including our most recent release of the 2012 &lt;a href=&quot;http://gis.phila.gov/arcgis/rest/services/PhilaOIT-GIS_Boundaries/MapServer/12&quot;&gt;State House&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://gis.phila.gov/arcgis/rest/services/PhilaOIT-GIS_Boundaries/MapServer/13&quot;&gt;State Senatorial&lt;/a&gt;, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://gis.phila.gov/arcgis/rest/services/PhilaOIT-GIS_Boundaries/MapServer/14&quot;&gt;U.S. Congressional Districts&lt;/a&gt;, clipped to the Philadelphia city limits. These services can be mashed up with other geographic data to produce new insights about our city and neighborhoods. From mapping &lt;a href=&quot;http://gis.phila.gov/arcgis/rest/services/PhilaGov/Parks/MapServer&quot;&gt;parks&lt;/a&gt; by congressional district, to counting &lt;a href=&quot;http://gis.phila.gov/ArcGIS/rest/services/PhilaGov/Healthy_Corner_Stores/MapServer&quot;&gt;healthy corner stores&lt;/a&gt; by census tract, the number of projects these services can support is endless. So visit &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phila.gov/map#id=8f9ba847d9de429db24cfc83d18cf949&quot;&gt;phila.gov/map&lt;/a&gt;, select your region, and start mapping some data!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Think of something you want to build but can’t find data anywhere? Maybe we’re already working on it, but if not visit opendataphilly and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opendataphilly.org/opendata/nominate/?sort=rating_score&amp;amp;dir=desc&quot;&gt;nominate a dataset&lt;/a&gt;. A future release could be closer than you think.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://hamhands.github.io/words/announcing-new-spatial-web-services</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hamhands.github.io/words/announcing-new-spatial-web-services</guid>
        
        <category>Philadelphia</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>From Open Data to Big Data</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At all levels, &lt;a href=&quot;http://datacatalogs.org/&quot;&gt;governments around the world&lt;/a&gt; are opening their data in order to better engage their citizenry and foster the development of new solutions to long-standing problems. If governments are serious about this mission, and if they want to harness the true power of open data, they must release with intent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Philadelphia Mayor Michael Nutter adopted a formal open data policy in April of 2012, we at the City of Philadelphia have taken steps to build an effective and durable open data infrastructure. Working with partners in both the private and public sector, we make our data available not only on static datastores, but via dynamic channels, allowing for continued feedback and collaboration. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opendataphilly.org/&quot;&gt;OpenDataPhilly&lt;/a&gt;, the portal for open data in Philadelphia, allows users to offer comments, suggest and nominate new datasets, as well as submit project examples. More recently, we have begun to leverage the public software code sharing platform &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/cityofphiladelphia&quot;&gt;GitHub&lt;/a&gt; as a new platform for our open data. As we continue to utilize new future, citizens will be able to see how data grows and changes, allowing for another level of transparency and engagement.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The true power of government data is unlocked when it is used to build new solutions, services, and visualizations. Rather than simply dumping giant sets of data into public repositories, our releases are designed with specific intent – to be readily accessible and digestible so that they can be easily incorporated into any number of different civic projects. Some of our most dynamic datasets are available through a number of &lt;a href=&quot;http://phlapi.com/&quot;&gt;Application Protocol Interfaces (APIs)&lt;/a&gt;, allowing users to quickly retrieve data in as little time as it takes to write a query. These interfaces provide real-time updates, allowing developers to build apps that reflect changes in the data over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/img/axis_crime.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;AxisPhilly RIP&quot; /&gt;
&lt;em&gt;AxisPhilly’s Crime Change App is a great example of how city data can be leveraged by the public.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Released in concert with the Philadelphia Police Department, the Philadelphia Crime Data API has proven to be one of our most popular offerings, with the data serving as the platform for solutions built by both government and outside developers from around the Philadelphia region. Axis Philly’s Crime Change Map, built by developer &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/caseypt&quot;&gt;Casey Thomas&lt;/a&gt;, shows percent change for different types of crimes by neighborhood over time, allowing for both temporal and spatial comparison. Harnessing the dynamic nature of the API, developer &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/davewalk&quot;&gt;David Walk&lt;/a&gt; put together &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.phlcrimemapper.com/&quot;&gt;PHL Crime Mapper&lt;/a&gt;, which allows users to search for all crime incidents by extent and time, with results as current as two days and as old as three years prior. Coming from outside of the city and highlighting the API’s utility to civic hackers, Boston coder &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/mapmeld&quot;&gt;Nick Doiron&lt;/a&gt; created a mashup of crime hotspots and Google routing data to show the relative danger of a user-defined walking route. Solutions like these highlight the power of data when it is released with the specific goal of being used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Uses of city data such as those mentioned above not only create valuable services for our citizenry, but also greatly inform the work we do in city government. Outside developers and researchers coming from diverse sectors and backgrounds can see new uses for data that we may not have thought of, as those closest to a problem may often miss opportunities for innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As more of our data is released with the intent that outside developers will make use of it, an added – almost unanticipated – benefit of open data is that we are starting to see opportunities for new internal uses for our data. Our work to make data more usable benefits not only those outside, but data users in other departments and agencies of government. This helps underscore the connection between the work being done on open data and the promise of “big data” to help enable better decisions and investments by government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Open data programs help governments think more strategically about how their data is used. This will have ramifications for how those outside government make use of data, and for how we use it ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
        <link>http://hamhands.github.io/words/from-open-data-to-big-data</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hamhands.github.io/words/from-open-data-to-big-data</guid>
        
        <category>Philadelphia</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
