<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Hamhanded.ly</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</description>
    <link>http://hamhands.github.io//</link>
    <atom:link href="http://hamhands.github.io//feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2014 17:56:00 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Nov 2014 17:56:00 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v2.4.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Embracing Idiocy</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Let me begin with the following admission: &lt;strong&gt;I’m sort of an idiot.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, so that’s a term with an &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Idiot&quot;&gt;extremely offensive history&lt;/a&gt;, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xnELqa8vgj0&quot;&gt;let me explain&lt;/a&gt;. What I mean is that I tend to screw up a lot. On a daily basis I probably spend around 5-10% of my time cleaning up after some mistake, attempting to save face after doing something kinda dumb, or just avoiding the cycle of beating myself up for not knowing something I should know. I never really feel like an expert about anything, even the things I’m supposed to be good enough to charge for. How I’ve survived for as long as I have is a complete mystery. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you click away (who wants to read what an idiot has to say, right?), here’s the point: in some ways, idiocy is a good thing. Screwing up is rad. In fact, it’s maybe the best thing people can do. Startups throw around the idea of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thedailybeast.com/articles/2014/01/05/fail-fast-fail-often-how-losing-can-help-you-win.html&quot;&gt;failing fast&lt;/a&gt; a lot, which beyond being one of those buzz phrases that I hate even though I just invoked it, the idea is that taking risks is how businesses innovate. Chocolate chip cookies were a mistake and we all love those, right? Sure &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chocolate_chip_cookie#History&quot;&gt;Ruth Graves Wakefield&lt;/a&gt; made a rookie move, but it was because she was trying to do one thing kinda boring right and ended up creating something way more longlasting and exciting by doing it wrong. She didn’t spend hours fretting over doing it the right way. She didn’t read the instruction manual and it worked out way better because of it. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What this means for the individual (i.e me) is that messing up is a critical component of learning. I know, I know, &lt;strong&gt;huge revelation&lt;/strong&gt;, but this is a pretty foundational point. If kids don’t have the negative reinforcement life hands them when they skin their knee, they won’t learn limits. They won’t become good cyclists because they won’t know how far they can lean on turns. More than that, if they don’t learn this lesson under safe conditions, they might screw up in traffic and really hurt themselves. Mistakes are great, not because they show you not to do something, but when they show you &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; you shouldn’t do something. When you can see why exactly it is that one course of action isn’t preferable, you can extrapolate and bend the rules more than you can if you just obey orders. If you can see why x action might lead to y outcome, you can do more to lower the risk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conversely, fear of failure is one of the biggest obstacles to doing really cool things. I am extremely afraid of failure. Whenever I have an idea, my default response is to come up with a litany of reasons why it might fail. It doesn’t matter if those reasons are likely or not, but the mere weight of so many possible fail-points typically robs me of the energy to pursue the thought. I’m really good at killing ideas before they have the time to grow. The only time I don’t do this is when I don’t know enough to talk myself out of something. In other words, the only times I allow myself enough leeway to make a mistake is when I’m too ignorant about something to know I’m going to make a mistake.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So JFDI, stop asking for permission, &lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 28 Nov 2014 08:41:30 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://hamhands.github.io//learning/2014/11/28/embracing-idiocy.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://hamhands.github.io//learning/2014/11/28/embracing-idiocy.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>learning</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
